<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Syllabus>
<CourseTitle><subject name="History">HIST</subject> <courseNum num="011">011</courseNum> <courseName>World History II</courseName></CourseTitle>
<Prof who="PC">Patrick Cosby, <qual>Ph. D.</qual></Prof>
<email>phc14@psu.edu154 </email>
<officeHours><locations type="virtual">KochelVirtual Office Hours</locations>:<days>MTWTh</days> <time type="PM">><start>1:00</start>-<end>2:00</end></time> <note>Or by appointment</note></officeHours> 

<courseObjectives type="list"><sectionTitle>I. Objectives</sectionTitle>:  <p>This course is intended to introduce students to the variety of cultures and ideas that have shaped our modern world. It surveys world history from the period of European expansion to our current age. We will explore the factors that led to the networks of exchange and the encounters that connected the peoples of the world long before our current phase of <term>“globalization.”</term> We inhabit a world in which the fragments of the past continue to shape and influence our lives, and this course is intended as a first step toward understanding our place in a larger human story.The course is organized around four distinct, but often overlapping themes. The development of these four themes have shaped our modern world through the last 500 years and continue to present challenges for contemporary life.</p> 

<objective number="1">1. <topic>Global Capitalism</topic>: Global Connections through trade, colonialism, and travel accelerated with the European conquest of the Americas and the integration of the Atlantic World as a new cultural and economic sphere. Through subsequent centuries, capitalism expanded as the industrial revolution and colonialism brought distant parts of the globe into an expanding market and inspired new forms of dissent and conflict. The wars of the twentieth century witnessed the rise of global, neoliberal capitalism as other ideological alternatives faltered. Contemporary conflicts and crises are largely the result of disputes over the costs and consequences of capitalist global expansion.</objective> 

<objective number="2">2. <topic>Violence and Colonialism</topic>: War and violence are not exclusive to the modern world, but the scale and destructiveness of violence in the modern age have drawn entire industrial nations into catastrophic war, as nuclear weapons have threatened all life on the planet. Wars have been fought over political power, religion, ideology, or access to economic resources or labor. In many cases, violence has been justified by dehumanizing enemy combatants as the “Other” in order to inflict unimaginable destruction. The legacies of these conflicts have left deep scars and continue to influence the ways in which people around the world relate to each other.</objective> 

<objective number="3">3. <topic>The Politics of Difference</topic>: As human societies encountered each other through trade and violence, people often justified colonialism and conflict by focusing on differences in race, gender or sexualities, ethnicity, class, religion, nationality, or ideology. Legacies of colonialism, slavery, nationalism, and patriarchy have left a mark on modern history. Through the past centuries, and increasingly since the late twentieth century, activists and mass movements have challenged and attempted to overcome politics marked by socially or culturally constructed differences. Contemporary politics are still defined by ongoing efforts to overcome differences and a countervailing effort to preserve or assert inequality and privilege.</objective> 

<objective number="4">4: <topic>Environment and Society</topic>: Human societies have always altered their natural environments and adapted to environmental change. From paleoindians hunting megafauna to extinction to the development of agriculture some 10,0000 years ago, the natural world has been shaped by, and 
influenced in turn, the evolution of human societies. In modern world history, however, developments have redefined the dynamic interaction between the environment and society. The natural world has been redefined as merely a reservoir of “natural resources,” industrialization and the modern age of nuclear weapons/ petrochemicals threaten the “goldilocks conditions” that sustain life on this planet, and mass political movements have emerged to seek social and technological solutions to environmental challenges.</objective></courseObjectives>     

<p>In addition, the course will introduce you to the specific disciplinary skills of historical thinking</p>: 

<numberedList>
<skill number="1">1) The ability to analyze questions of historical agency and contingency, causation, comparison across cultures and over time, and change/ continuity over time</skill>

<skill number="2">2) The ability to read primary and secondary sources analytically and critically</skill>    

<skill number="3">3) The ability to synthesize information from a variety of sources and draw meaningful conclusions</skill>

<skill number="4">4) The ability to construct and express arguments that are supported by credible evidence and address major historical questions</skill>

<skill number="5">5) The ability to recognize and evaluate different historical interpretations and historical debates.II. Course FormatThe format of this class is designed to make the best use of our resources and our time together. It will combine lectures, supplemental readings and videos, and interactive in-class discussions. That means I will not be just a talking head at the front of the room. It will require you to do significant work outside of the classroom to prepare, and to engage in discussions.</skill></numberedList>
</Syllabus>
